Away from all land
The ocean
It covers more
than half the surface of our planet
And yet
for the most part
it is
beyond our reach
Much of it is
virtually empty
A watery desert
All life
that is here
is locked in a
constant search to find food
A struggle to
conserve precious energy
in the open ocean
The biggest
of all fish
30 tons in weight
12 metres long
The whale shark
Its huge bulk is
sustained by near microscopic creatures of the sea
Plankton
Whale sharks
cruise on regular habitual routes
between the
best feeding grounds
In February
that takes them
to the surface waters
far from the
coast of Venezuela
Others are
already here
Bait fish have
come for the same reason
to feed on
the plankton
The whale shark
has timed its arrival exactly right
Oddly
the tiny fish
swarm around it
They're using
it as a shield
Other predatory
fish are lurking nearby
Yellowfin tuna
They seem
wary of the giant
The shark dives
as if to escape
from such overcrowding
Now the tuna
have a chance
to attack the
unprotected baitfish
But then
back comes
the giant
It has taken a
vast mouthful of the baitfish itself
Plankton it seems
is not the
only food
for a whale shark
Both shark and
tuna feast together
But the tuna
must beware
Even they can end
up in the whale shark's stomach
Predators here
must grab what they can when they can
For such events
do not last long
The dense shoals
on which so many depend
gather only when
water conditions are perfect
Many predators spend much of their time cruising the open ocean
endlessly
searching
Plankton
feeding rays do so
gliding with
minimum effort
The oceanic
white tip shark
Another energy
efficient traveller
It specialises in
locating prey in the emptiest areas of the open ocean
Patrolling the
top 100 metres of water
Taste in water is
the equivalent of smell in the air
An oceanic white
tip is able to detect even the faintest trace
Small pilot
fish swim with it
The shark can
find prey far more easily than they can
and they'll be
able to collect the scraps from its meals
Its long fixed
pectoral fins
enable it to
soar through the water
with the least
expenditure of energy
This shark has
found a school of rainbow runners
It would eat one
given the chance
But rainbow
runners are swift and agile
and not
easily caught
So it
bides its time
There's a chance
that eventually
it may spot a
weakened fish
that's catchable
The hunter
endlessly waiting
Excitement
far from land
A school
of dolphin
500 strong
They've sensed
there's food around
And they're
racing to catch up with it
The news
has spread
now a number of
schools are on their way
They're heading
towards the Azores
volcanic islands
a thousand miles west of Portugal
The dolphin scan
the water ahead with their sonar
They're close
to their target
This is it
Scad mackerel
It's difficult
for a single dolphin to catch the fish
To avoid
wasting energy
they work
as a group
They drive
the fish upwards
trapping them
against the surface
And there
other predators await them
Cory shearwaters
They're waiting
for the dolphin
to drive the prey
closer to the surface
Now the shearwaters can dive down on them
descending to
20 metres or more
And the dolphins
block the bait balls retreat
The dolphins leave as soon as they've had their fill
And at last the mackerel sink below the diving range of the birds
As the sun
disappears
a profound change
takes place in the ocean
Deep water plankton start to rise from the depths
And another
hungry army prepares to receive it
Every night
wherever
conditions are right
countless millions of creatures from the deep
migrate to
the surface
seeking food
A baby sailfish
15cm long
snaps up
everything in its path
In three
years time
it'll be one of
the ocean's most formidable hunters
weighing 60 kilos
Just now，however
it's very
vulnerable
These manta
rays are giants
8 metres across
and weighing over two tons
The bladelike
projections on either side of the head
help to steer
plankton into the manta's mouth
Dawn returns
and the plankton
sinks back into the depths
If we are
to follow
we must use
a submarine
As we descend
into the darkness
The pressure builds
The temperature falls
Below 500 metres
new mysterious
animals appear
Their
bizarre shapes
help them to
remain suspended
In the dark space
Some resemble
creatures familiar from shallower waters
Others defy
classification
All around
organic particles drift downwards
Marine snow
detritus from
the creatures
swarming in the
sunlit waters above
The snow is food
for many animals here
like the
sea spider
a small relative
of shrimps and crabs
Those strange
leglike appendages
are feathered to
stop it from sinking
They can also
enmesh marine snow
which it wipes
carefully into its jaws
A sawtooth eel
hangs upright and motionless
Gazing
ever upwards
it watches for prey silhouetted against the faint glimmerings of light
from the surface
Days may pass
Before prey swims
close enough for it to strike
Farther down still
the blackness is complete
No vestige
of sunlight
can penetrate
as far as this
Food is
very scarce
And nothing can
afford to waste any energy
A Dumbo octopus
simply flaps a fin
No need for the
jet propulsion
used by its
shallow water relatives above
The weirdest in
this world of the strange
Vampyrotothys
the vampire
squid from hell
Disturb it
and it only
retreats a little distance
Go after it
and it has a
special defence
To see
what it does
you must
switch off the lights
The vampire squid
has lights of its own
Bioluminescent
bacteria shine from pockets on its arms
To confuse
its predators
Are those eyes？
In fact
there's spots at
the end of its mantle
A bite there
would leave the head unscathed
The threat
diminishes
and Vampiro Toothys disappears into the blackness
At last
the sea floor
Over two
miles down
The pressure here
is 300 times that at the surface
It takes
several months
for marine snow
to drift down as far as this
As you travel away from the rocky margins of the continents
An immense plain
stretches ahead
It extends for
thousands of miles
Gradually
sinking downwards
There are faint
trails in the ooze
Signs
that even here
there is life
These are what
made some of them
Sea urchins
sifting the accumulating drifts
Shrimps standing
on elegant tiptoe
fastidiously select the particles that appeal to them
But in
the deep sea
as everywhere else
if there
are grazers
there are hunters
A monkfish
almost indistinguishable from the sand
on which it lies
Why waste
energy chasing around
if you can
attract prey towards you
with a lure？
Maybe that one
was a bit big
The monkfish can
wait for days if necessary
until the
rightsized meal turns up
Scavengers on
the other hand
have to move
around to find their food
Crabs can detect
the faintest of tastes in the water
And that helps
them locate the latest body
To drift
down from above
Eels are already
feeding on the corpse
Isopods
like giant marine
woodlice a third of a meter long
are ripping into
the rotting flesh
Over the
next few hours
there'll be
frenzied competition
between
scavengers of all kinds
to grab a share
Just occasionally
there is a
gigantic bonanza
The remains of
a sperm whale
He died five
months or so ago
There's little
left but fatty blubber
clinging
to its bones
Its flesh has
nourished life for miles around
But now the
feast is almost over
Spider crabs
a metre across
still pick at the
last putrid remains
A few weeks more
and nothing will
be left but bare bones
The crabs
will have to fast
until the next
carcass drifts down
But not all food
comes from the sunlit world above
The floor of
the Atlantic Ocean
is split in two
by an immense
volcanic mountain chain
That winds unbroken for 45，000 miles around the globe
In places
it's riven by
great fissures
From which
superheated water
loaded with
dissolved minerals
blasts into
the icy depths
Clouds of sulphides solidify into towering chimneys
as tall as a
threestorey house
At 400 degrees
this scalding
cocktail of chemicals
would be lethally
toxic to most forms of life
But astoundingly
a particular kind
of bacteria thrives here
and feeding
on the bacteria
vast numbers of shrimps
So beyond the
farthest reach of the sun's power
A rich independent community exists
That draws all its energy directly from the earth's molten core
On the other
side of the planet
in the western
Pacific bordering Japan
the dragon chimneys
another series of
hot vents erupting in the darkness
Here，more
but different
bacteria thrive in a similar way
And here too
more crustaceans
but quite different species from those around the hot vents in the Atlantic
These are
squat lobsters
clad in
furry armour
jostling
with one another
beside the jets
of superheated water
for the
best places
from which to
graze on bacteria
These vents too
like those in
the Atlantic
are isolated oases
So widely
separated
that each
community is unique
Cross to the
other side of the Pacific
to the deep near
the Galapagos Islands
And there are
yet other fissures
venting
superheated water
One and a
half miles down
at a site
known as Nine North
towering chimneys
support a spectacular display
of giant
tube worms
These vents give
off so much energy
that some of the
worms reach three metres in length
They're the fastest growing marine invertebrates known
All told
over 50
different species
Have so far been
found living here
The inhabitants
of these bustling communities
may grow
and speed
But their
existence can also be short
For the vents do
not erupt indefinitely
Suddenly
unpredictably
they may
become inactive
Nine months have
passed at Nine North
What were only
recently chimneys teeming with life
Have turned into cold
sterile
mineral monuments
Some eddy deep in
the earth's crust
diverted the
volcanic energy elsewhere
And an entire
microworld was extinguished
In places
volcanoes have
erupted to build great submarine mountains
There are thought
to be around 30，000 such volcanoes
Some
measured from
the sea floor
are taller
than Everest
Sheer cliffs
soaring to drowned volcanic peaks
Powerful currents
sweep up the mountain's flanks
transporting nutrients from deep water towards the summits
The hard rock
provides excellent anchorage
for communities
of great variety
and stunning colour
Soft corals
several
metres across
collect the
marine snow
as it drifts past
Whip corals
stretch out into the current
Giant sponges
filter nourishment
from the
cold water
A richly varied
community flourishes here
sustained by the
nutrients and detritus
in the icy currents that flow around the peak
Yet it is all
blossoming on an extinct volcano
a mile below the
reach of the sun
Anoatetus
It spends its
days hiding 400 metres down
But as night falls
it ascends up to
the reefs to look for food
Its graceful shell contains gasfilled flotation chambers
that
control its depth
It's powered by a
jet of water squirting from a siphon
But it
travels shell first
so it can't see
exactly where it's going
Its nearest living relatives are squid and octopus
which over
evolutionary time
have both
lost their shells
And the octopus has become one of the nautilus's major predators
It's a
master of disguise
The nautilus
keeps well clear of them
Its small tentacles carry highly developed chemical sensors
which can detect
traces of both predators and prey
It uses its water
jet to dig in the sand
Because it devotes so little energy to swimming
It only needs a
meal once a month
Got something
And just as well
dawn is
approaching
and it has to
puff its way back to deeper waters
30 miles away
shoals of squid
are jetting upwards towards the surface
By night
they seek small
fish among the plankton
but they'
re cautious
Pacific
spotted dolphin
They're guided
by their sonar
The dolphins
as so often
are working as a team
Synchronising
their attacks
to confuse
their prey
As dawn approaches
squid and
fish and plankton
retreat downwards
to shelter in
the darkness
Some of these
isolated volcanoes
rise as much as 9
000 metres from the sea floor
reaching close
to the surface
Around these
peaks invigorated by daily sunshine
marine life
flourishes in spectacular abundance
Fish crowd here
because the volcano forces nutrients to the surface
encouraging the
plankton to bloom
An oceanic wanderer
a mola mola
stops by to be
cleaned by reef fish
at the sea
mount edge
Butterfly fish
pluck stringlike parasites from its flanks
The huge fish lives on jellyfish over a thousand metres down
where the water
is twenty degrees colder
So
a brush up
near the surface
allows it
to warm up
before making
more deep water forays
The summit of
this volcanic mountain
rises above the
surface of the sea
It's Ascension Island
800 miles from
any other land
A welcome vital
haven for long distance travellers
Frigate birds
spend months continuously airborne at sea
But at
nesting time
they come to a
scission from all over the ocean
The island's
barren slopes of volcanic ash and lava
Might seem to
offer perfectly good sites for a nest
But the frigates
choose an even more isolated site
Bosunbird Island
a lonely pillar
just off Ascension's coast
Frigates are the
world's lightest bird
relative to
their wingspan
And they can soar
for weeks on end
with
minimal effort
They seem much
more at home in the skies
Than in a
crowded colony on land
But nest they must
They come from all over the Atlantic to this their only colony
There are
boobies here too
To raise
their young
sea birds worldwide seek such remote islands
Swimmers also
come to Ascension to breed
A female green
turtle approaches the coast
She's not eaten
once in two months
She may have travelled 1000 miles from her feeding grounds
The greatest
journey of her kind
Many others
are here too
resting on the
sandy sea floor
awaiting the
darkness of night
when it'll be
safer to visit the beaches
Eggs that were laid a few weeks ago at the start of the season
are beginning to hatch
Most hatchings
happen at night
Now
in the
light of day
the young are
extremely vulnerable
They must get to
the sea as soon as possible
But their trials
have only just begun
Many will drown
in the pounding waves
During the
next 20 years
the vast majority
will inevitably die
But those that
survive will eventually
as their mothers
did before them
return to the
very same beach
where they
were hatched
How they find
their way back
across thousands
of miles of open ocean
we still
have no idea
A frigate saw us
Somewhere beneath
the surface below
there is the
food it must have
But where？
Those that fly
above the ocean
must be able to
read the signs of fresh supplies
or perish
100 miles from
the Mexican coast
and keen eyes
have spotted movement
Sailfish
three metres long
are closing
in on prey
They will only
use just enough energy to make their kill
Never wasting
a fin stroke
Nearly a hundred sailfish have surrounded a single school of baitfish
It's very rare to
see so many of these hunters in one place
To herd their prey
the predators
raise their huge dorsal fins
A mistimed
strike by one selfish
could fatally
damage another
But each continually changes its colour
From blue to
stripes to black
That warns its
companions of its intentions
And also
confuses the prey
As the shoal is
driven nearer the surface
It comes within
the range of the seabirds
Out here in
the open ocean
There is nowhere
for the baitfish to hide
Sailfish live a
high octane life
To survive
they must
find prey daily
So their entire
existence will be spent on the move
Over 90% of the
living space for life on our planet
is in the oceans
Home to the
biggest animal that exists
or has
ever existed
The blue whale
Some weigh
nearly 200 tons
twice the size of
the largest dinosaur
Despite
their great size
we still
have little idea
of where they
travel in the vast oceans
And none at all
of where they go to breed
The largest animal on Earth feeds almost exclusively
on one of
the smallest
krill
shrimplike
crustaceans
They take many
tonnes of water
into their
ballooning throats in a single gulp
and sieve out
what it contains
Every day
each one swallows
some four million krill
Such gargantuan harvests
depend on the
continuing fertility of the oceans
But global changes now threaten the great blooms of plankton
on which the
whales depend
Once
and not
so long ago
300，000 blue
whales roamed the oceans
Now
less than 3% of
that number remains
Our planet is
still full of wonders
As we explore them
so we gain not
only understanding
but power
It's not just the
future of the whale that today lies in our hands
It's the survival
of the natural world
In all parts of
the living planet
We can now destroy
or we can cherish
The choice is ours